[Bloom Life]
[بلوم لايف]
[2016]
[2016]
I envy you so much.
I envy you so much.
You are leaving here soon.
You are leaving here soon.
I'm just going to Shanghai for college.
I'm just going to Shanghai for college.
It's not like I'm never coming back.
It's not like I'm never coming back.
No.
No.
You need to travel further and see more of the world.
You need to travel further and see more of the world.
You're the best student among the three of us.
You're the best student among the three of us.
You need to study hard,
You need to study hard,
find a good job,
find a good job,
date the boy you like,
date the boy you like,
and wear the clothes you want to wear.
and wear the clothes you want to wear.
You should live a brilliant life,
You should live a brilliant life,
twice as brilliant,
twice as brilliant,
three times as brilliant.
three times as brilliant.
Your eyes are our eyes.
Your eyes are our eyes.
You need to see the world for us,
You need to see the world for us,
okay?
okay?
[Episode 8: I Spent a Long Vacation Here]
[Episode 8: I Spent a Long Vacation Here]
Minawar.
ميناوار.
I've been so tied up lately.
I've been so tied up lately.
I couldn't make it to your wedding and childbirth.
I couldn't make it to your wedding and childbirth.
This is my gift.
This is my gift.
I'll get going.
I'll get going.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Who is he?
Who is he?
An old friend who has just come back from abroad.
An old friend who has just come back from abroad.
Abroad?
Abroad?
It seems there's a new dance audition
It seems there's a new dance audition
in the troupe recently. I want to give it a try.
in the troupe recently. I want to give it a try.
Audition?
Audition?
You're a mother now, and you still want to audition?
You're a mother now, and you still want to audition?
What are you thinking about every day?
What are you thinking about every day?
I'm asking you who he is.
I'm asking you who he is.
I told you, he's my—
I told you, he's my—
Don't yell!
Don't yell!
It's fruiting!
It's fruiting!
It's bearing fruit just in time for the opening tomorrow.
It's bearing fruit just in time for the opening tomorrow.
It definitely means it will be a huge success.
It definitely means it will be a huge success.
You just put it here.
You just put it here.
Hey, no, no, no.
Hey, no, no, no.
It looks so good.
It looks so good.
So pretty.
So pretty.
I didn't fire this well.
I didn't fire this well.
It's still matte.
It's still matte.
I need to apply another layer of transparent glaze
I need to apply another layer of transparent glaze
and re-fire it.
and re-fire it.
Looks fine to me.
Looks fine to me.
I think it's pretty good.
I think it's pretty good.
Arzugul, what are you doing?
Arzugul, what are you doing?
I want to call Minawar
I want to call Minawar
and ask her to come over and dance.
and ask her to come over and dance.
Dance at the opening ceremony?
Dance at the opening ceremony?
I don't think I can.
I don't think I can.
I haven't danced for months.
I haven't danced for months.
I'm afraid I'll make a fool of myself.
I'm afraid I'll make a fool of myself.
Why can't you?
Why can't you?
Isn't dancing what you're most familiar with?
Isn't dancing what you're most familiar with?
Doing what you know best
Doing what you know best
in the place you know best, why can't you?
in the place you know best, why can't you?
Exactly. Just come over.
Exactly. Just come over.
We're all here.
We're all here.
You must come tomorrow.
You must come tomorrow.
It's settled.
It's settled.
What are you doing in there?
What are you doing in there?
The baby is crying so hard.
The baby is crying so hard.
Come out and nurse her.
Come out and nurse her.
This is where the old kitchen was.
This is where the old kitchen was.
It's also become a guest room now.
It's also become a guest room now.
I've redesigned the whole space.
I've redesigned the whole space.
Each guest room has its own theme.
Each guest room has its own theme.
This one here is our music-themed room.
This one here is our music-themed room.
That one is our food-theme room.
That one is our food-theme room.
Great guy.
Great guy.
Smart girl.
Smart girl.
Dad,
Dad,
I didn't fire this jar well.
I didn't fire this jar well.
I originally used a darker blue,
I originally used a darker blue,
but I don't know why
but I don't know why
it turned out lighter after firing.
it turned out lighter after firing.
Not knowing what color
Not knowing what color
it will turn out
it will turn out
is what makes earthenware interesting.
is what makes earthenware interesting.
This is your masterpiece.
This is your masterpiece.
From now on, just follow your own ideas
From now on, just follow your own ideas
to make earthenware.
to make earthenware.
[The Symbiosis of All Things: Laili Batur]
[The Symbiosis of All Things: Laili Batur]
1, 2, 3!
1, 2, 3!
[Soaring Dove Homestay]
[Soaring Dove Homestay]
Congratulations.
Congratulations.
This is the tapestry I brought back for you.
This is the tapestry I brought back for you.
Thank you. It's beautiful.
شكراً لك. إنه جميل.
Where should we hang it?
أين ينبغي أن نعلقها؟
Hang it on the first floor.
علّقها في الطابق الأول.
The first floor.
الطابق الأول.
Okay.
تمام.
Why isn't Minawar here yet?
لماذا لم يصل ميناوار بعد؟
Sorry, I'm late.
معذرةً، لقد تأخرت.
Here she is.
ها هي ذي.
We were just waiting for you.
كنا ننتظرك فقط.
We're waiting for you to dance the finale.
ننتظرك لتؤدي رقصة الختام.
I don't really know how to dance anymore.
لم أعد أعرف كيف أرقص حقاً.
I haven't danced in so long.
لم أرقص منذ مدة طويلة.
I'd rather not embarrass myself.
أفضّل ألا أحرج نفسي.
How come you can't dance?
لماذا لا تستطيع الرقص؟
You're so good at it.
أنت بارع جداً في ذلك.
Let's have a drink.
هيا نشرب.
Cheers.
هتافات.
It's delicious.
إنه لذيذ.
I've been meaning to tell you.
كنت أنوي إخبارك بذلك.
Thank you for the costume you gave me last time.
شكراً لك على الزي الذي أهديتني إياه في المرة الماضية.
Even though I
على الرغم من أنني
might never be able to dance again,
قد لا يتمكن من الرقص مرة أخرى،
seeing that costume
رؤية ذلك الزي
made me see my old self.
جعلني ذلك أرى نفسي القديمة.
What do you mean you won't dance?
ماذا تقصد بأنك لن ترقص؟
You were and still are the most beautiful.
كنتِ وما زلتِ الأجمل.
Who was it that determined, since childhood,
من كان مصمماً على ذلك منذ الطفولة؟
to dance at the foot of Muztagh Ata?
الرقص عند سفح جبل موستاج آتا؟
Then everyone,
ثم الجميع،
how about we go see the golden sunrise on the mountain together?
ما رأيك أن نذهب معًا لمشاهدة شروق الشمس الذهبي على الجبل؟
Sure.
بالتأكيد.
I think you are born for dancing.
أعتقد أنك وُلدت للرقص.
I believe you also want to keep dancing.
أعتقد أنك ترغب أيضاً في الاستمرار بالرقص.
Cheers.
هتافات.
Hello, boss. Check out.
مرحباً سيدي. تفضل بالانصراف.
Okay.
تمام.
Xia Zi.
شيا زي.
Which room?
أي غرفة؟
The earthenware room inside.
غرفة الأواني الفخارية بالداخل.
Follow me.
اتبعني.
Hope you enjoyed your stay.
أتمنى أن تكون قد استمتعت بإقامتك.
This room is pretty good.
هذه الغرفة جيدة جداً.
Yes, the environment is great.
نعم، البيئة رائعة.
All right, it's all done.
حسناً، لقد انتهى كل شيء.
Please help us promote it.
ساعدونا في الترويج له.
Definitely.
قطعاً.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Have a good time.
وقتا ممتعا.
Your car is at the door.
سيارتك عند الباب.
Okay, thank you.
حسناً، شكراً لك.
This mung bean pillow
وسادة من حبوب المونج
is best for the baby.
الأفضل للطفل.
It keeps the baby's head from getting flat.
فهو يمنع رأس الطفل من أن يصبح مسطحاً.
When you were little,
عندما كنت صغيراً،
you weren't as obedient as Aliya.
لم تكن مطيعاً مثل علياء.
Whenever I put you in the cradle,
كلما وضعتك في المهد،
you would cry and make a fuss.
كنت ستبكي وتحدث ضجة.
You had to hold my arm to sleep.
كان عليك أن تمسك بذراعي حتى أنام.
I've read the National Arts Fund project
لقد قرأت مشروع الصندوق الوطني للفنون
you showed me
لقد أريتني
last time.
آخر مرة.
This project is specifically
هذا المشروع مخصص تحديدًا
for dance talents in Xinjiang.
للمواهب الراقصة في شينجيانغ.
The teachers are all dancers.
جميع المعلمين راقصون.
This opportunity is too good for you.
هذه الفرصة أفضل من أن تضيعها.
It's tailor-made for a star dancer like you.
إنه مصمم خصيصاً لراقصة نجمة مثلك.
I'm not a star dancer anymore.
لم أعد راقصة نجمة.
The current star is Gulistan.
النجم الحالي هو جولستان.
Nonsense.
هراء.
Actually.
في الحقيقة.
I came here this time
لقد أتيت إلى هنا هذه المرة
to ask you to help me
أطلب منك مساعدتي
take care of Aliya for a while.
اعتني بعلياء لبعض الوقت.
You've made up your mind?
هل حسمت أمرك؟
As long as it's something you truly want to do,
طالما أنه شيء ترغب حقًا في القيام به،
just go ahead and do it.
هيا، افعلها.
No matter where you go,
أينما ذهبت،
I'll always support you.
سأدعمك دائماً.
We've got things covered here at home.
الأمور تحت السيطرة هنا في المنزل.
No matter
لا يهم
where that person goes,
إلى أين يذهب ذلك الشخص،
they are looking
إنهم يبحثون
at the same moon as you.
في نفس القمر الذي أنت فيه.
Laili,
ليلي،
I want to discuss something with you.
أريد مناقشة أمر ما معك.
Go ahead.
تفضل.
This money
هذا المال
is from your part-time job over the past six months.
هذا المبلغ ناتج عن وظيفتك بدوام جزئي خلال الأشهر الستة الماضية.
Dad.
أب.
I saved it all for you.
لقد ادخرت كل شيء من أجلك.
Take it back.
ارجعه.
Take it.
خذها.
This workshop
ورشة العمل هذه
will be handed over to you.
سيتم تسليمها إليك.
I believe you can make better earthenware.
أعتقد أنه بإمكانك صنع أوانٍ فخارية أفضل.
Dad.
أب.
Take the money,
خذ المال،
go out,
الخروج،
and see the world.
ورؤية العالم.
And also see
وانظر أيضًا
how other people
كيف حال الآخرين
make earthenware.
صنع الأواني الفخارية.
Mom, Dad.
أمي، أبي.
Why are you back so late again?
لماذا تأخرت في العودة مرة أخرى؟
Come here. I have something to say to you.
تعال إلى هنا. لديّ شيء أريد أن أقوله لك.
Are you kidding me?
هل تمزح معي؟
The kid is so young, and you want to stay in Shanghai for half a year?
الطفل صغير جداً، وتريد البقاء في شنغهاي لمدة نصف عام؟
What kind of mother does that?
أي نوع من الأمهات يفعل ذلك؟
I provide you with a good life in this big house,
سأوفر لك حياة كريمة في هذا المنزل الكبير،
yet all you want to do is expose yourself in public.
لكن كل ما تريدينه هو أن تكشفي عن نفسك في الأماكن العامة.
Who knows what man you were out meeting
من يدري أي رجل كنتِ تقابلين؟
coming home so late at night?
هل تعود إلى المنزل في وقت متأخر من الليل؟
I am your wife, not your caged bird.
أنا زوجتك، لست طائرك المحبوس.
I'll lay it on the line today.
سأكشف الحقيقة اليوم.
If you want to leave, I'll divorce you!
إذا أردتِ الرحيل، فسأطلقك!
Stop right there.
توقف هنا.
What does she mean?
ماذا تقصد؟
What are you doing?
ماذا تفعل؟
Go ahead without worry. I'll take care of things at home.
انطلق دون قلق. سأهتم بالأمور في المنزل.
Do you remember when Arzugul left for Shanghai
هل تتذكر عندما غادرت أرزغول إلى شنغهاي؟
and we said goodbye at the alley entrance?
وهل ودعنا بعضنا عند مدخل الزقاق؟
You told me,
أخبرتني،
"It's best if you never come back."
"من الأفضل ألا تعود أبداً."
It's amazing.
إنه لأمر مذهل.
The one who said she would leave has stayed.
التي قالت إنها سترحل قد بقيت.
And the ones who stayed are leaving now.
والذين بقوا يغادرون الآن.
But we will definitely come back.
لكننا سنعود بالتأكيد.
I'll wait for you two to come back.
سأنتظر عودتكما.
Alright.
على ما يرام.
Go.
يذهب.
[Kashgar City—Shache County]
[مدينة كاشغر - مقاطعة شاتشي]
♪ Are these four lonely walls ♪
♪ هل هذه الجدران الأربعة وحيدة؟ ♪
♪ The sound of the dutar ♪
♪ صوت الدوتار ♪
♪ made my heart broken ♪
♪ حطمت قلبي ♪
♪ An empty bowl is enough ♪
♪ يكفي وعاء فارغ ♪
Parhat went to Urumqi
ذهب بارهات إلى أورومتشي
to study modern music.
لدراسة الموسيقى الحديثة.
I don't know when he'll be back.
لا أعرف متى سيعود.
He left this instrument behind.
لقد ترك هذه الآلة وراءه.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Xia Zi,
شيا زي,
I go to the Kizil Caves early
أذهب إلى كهوف كيزيل في وقت مبكر
every morning to make copies of the murals.
كل صباح لعمل نسخ من الجداريات.
[Kizil Caves, Cave 38 (Replica)]
[كهوف كيزيل، الكهف رقم 38 (نسخة طبق الأصل)]
Time passes very slowly
يمر الوقت ببطء شديد
while working here.
أثناء العمل هنا.
Every mural here
كل جدارية هنا
hides an ancient legend.
تخفي وراءها أسطورة قديمة.
A painting I have been working on recently
لوحة كنت أعمل عليها مؤخراً
has a moving story.
قصة مؤثرة.
Deep in the distant desert,
في أعماق الصحراء البعيدة،
a merchant caravan lost its way.
ضلت قافلة تجارية طريقها.
They plunged into a bottomless darkness
انغمسوا في ظلام لا قعر له
and were on the verge of death.
وكانوا على وشك الموت.
Amidst fear, hunger, and despair,
وسط الخوف والجوع واليأس،
Sa Bo, the merchant leader, was moved by compassion.
تأثر سا بو، زعيم التجار، بالشفقة.
He set himself on fire to light the way,
أشعل النار في نفسه لينير الطريق،
tearing through the eternal night.
يشق طريقه عبر الليل الأبدي.
In the faint light ignited
في الضوء الخافت اشتعل
by Sa Bo's fire of life,
بنار الحياة التي أشعلها سا بو،
the caravan escaped the predicament and survived.
نجت القافلة من المأزق.
When I was painting it,
عندما كنت أرسمها،
I kept thinking of your dad.
ظللت أفكر في والدك.
He also left a light
كما ترك ضوءًا
in our hearts.
في قلوبنا.
By the way,
بالمناسبة،
I have something
لدي شيء ما
to give you.
لأقدمه لك.
What is it? So mysterious.
ما هذا؟ إنه أمر غامض للغاية.
My dad's phone?
هاتف والدي؟
Why do you have it?
لماذا تمتلكه؟
Your mom gave it to me
أعطتني إياه والدتك
and asked me to fix it.
وطلب مني إصلاحه.
I took it with me when I went home last time,
أخذته معي عندما عدت إلى المنزل في المرة الماضية،
and they just mailed it back after fixing it.
وقاموا بإعادة إرسالها بالبريد بعد إصلاحها.
Zi,
يوم،
I just finished a surgery.
لقد انتهيت للتو من عملية جراحية.
A war has
لقد اندلعت حرب
started here.
بدأنا من هنا.
The hospital got busy all of a sudden.
أصبح المستشفى مزدحماً فجأة.
The more it's like this,
كلما ازداد الوضع على هذا النحو،
the more I miss you and your mom.
كلما اشتقت إليكِ وإلى والدتكِ، ازداد اشتياقي إليكِ وإلى والدتكِ.
The situation here is very bad.
الوضع هنا سيء للغاية.
I'm not sure
لست متأكداً
if I'll be able
إذا كنت سأتمكن
to go back and see you again.
لأعود وأراك مجدداً.
I'm not even sure
لست متأكداً حتى
if you'll ever see this video.
إذا شاهدت هذا الفيديو يوماً ما.
I've decided.
لقد قررت.
Record a video for me.
سجل لي فيديو.
Ready?
مستعد؟
I saw the video you recorded for me,
لقد شاهدت الفيديو الذي سجلته لي،
even though it was late.
على الرغم من تأخر الوقت.
Dad,
أب،
I miss you, too.
أفتقدك أيضًا.
That day,
في ذلك اليوم،
everyone was saying goodbye to you at the store.
كان الجميع يودعونك في المتجر.
Everyone talked about
الجميع يتحدثون عن
the last thing you said to them.
آخر شيء قلته لهم.
But I didn't say it.
لكنني لم أقل ذلك.
Because at that time,
لأنه في ذلك الوقت،
I wasn't ready to say goodbye to you at all.
لم أكن مستعداً لتوديعك على الإطلاق.
No matter what,
مهما حدث،
I want to tell you
أريد أن أخبرك
that you've always been my pride.
لطالما كنت فخري.
You've been independent and warm-hearted
لقد كنت مستقلاً وذا قلب طيب.
since you were little.
منذ صغرك.
That's just like me.
هذا يشبهني تماماً.
You have your own ideas,
لديك أفكارك الخاصة،
and you're stubborn.
وأنت عنيد.
That's just like your mom.
هذا يشبه والدتك تماماً.
But with your personality,
لكن بشخصيتك،
I'm always worried
أنا قلق دائماً
you'll
سوف
take a wrong turn.
يسلك منعطفاً خاطئاً.
But thinking about it now...
لكن بالتفكير في الأمر الآن...
Actually, it's not
في الحقيقة، ليس الأمر كذلك.
a bad thing for you to be like this.
من السيئ أن تكون هكذا.
No matter when,
بغض النظر عن الزمان،
just be yourself.
كن على طبيعتك.
You are my daughter,
أنتِ ابنتي،
but more importantly, you are yourself.
لكن الأهم من ذلك كله، أنك أنت نفسك.
You don't need to be like everyone else at all.
ليس عليك أن تكون مثل أي شخص آخر على الإطلاق.
I know.
أنا أعرف.
You always wanted me to have a stable
لطالما أردت أن أحظى باستقرار
and smooth life.
وحياة هانئة.
I have been trying hard.
لقد كنت أحاول جاهدًا.
I wanted to be that piece of the puzzle.
أردت أن أكون ذلك الجزء من اللغز.
But I was losing control more and more.
لكنني كنت أفقد السيطرة أكثر فأكثر.
I couldn't control my time
لم أستطع التحكم في وقتي
or my life.
أو حياتي.
to the point where I'd forgotten my own name.
لدرجة أنني نسيت اسمي.
My name is Xia Zi.
اسمي شيا زي.
I am your and Mom's daughter.
أنا ابنتك وابنة أمي.
I have the backing you gave me.
لقد حصلت على الدعم الذي قدمته لي.
So I'm not afraid.
لذلك أنا لست خائفاً.
I'm not afraid to fail
أنا لا أخشى الفشل
or start over.
أو ابدأ من جديد.
I can live the life I like.
أستطيع أن أعيش الحياة التي أحبها.
I can go find
يمكنني أن أذهب لأجد
where I truly belong,
حيث أنتمي حقاً،
though I haven't found it yet.
مع أنني لم أجده بعد.
Zi.
يوم.
You must remember,
يجب أن تتذكر،
Dad loves you.
أبي يحبك.
Dad
أب
will always love you.
سأحبك دائماً.
Dad.
أب.
I also want to tell you
أريد أيضاً أن أخبرك
that I love you, too.
أنا أحبك أيضاً.
Enjoy your stay.
استمتع بإقامتك.
[Soaring Dove Homestay]
[إقامة منزلية في سورينج دوف]
Xia Zi, look.
شيا زي، انظر.
Our account has gone viral recently.
لقد انتشر حسابنا بشكل واسع مؤخراً.
So many likes?
كل هذه الإعجابات؟
No wonder
لا عجب
two more booking orders just came in.
وصلت للتو طلبي حجز إضافيين.
I just got back.
لقد عدت للتو.
Why did you call me here?
لماذا استدعيتني إلى هنا؟
I still have a bunch of deliveries to make.
لا يزال لديّ الكثير من عمليات التسليم التي يجب القيام بها.
The cleaning lady had something come up
طرأ أمر ما على عاملة النظافة.
and can't make it today.
ولا أستطيع الحضور اليوم.
It's just one room upstairs—
إنها مجرد غرفة واحدة في الطابق العلوي—
the "Cinematic Memories" room.
غرفة "الذكريات السينمائية".
Can you help me clean it?
هل يمكنك مساعدتي في تنظيفه؟
♪ We are separated ♪
♪ لقد انفصلنا ♪
♪ Drifting in and out of the crowds ♪
♪ أتجول بين الحشود ♪
♪ Confining dusk within the dawn ♪
♪ حصر الغسق داخل الفجر ♪
♪ Waiting aimlessly for the traffic lights ♪
♪ انتظار إشارات المرور بلا هدف ♪
♪ Suddenly, I never ask again ♪
♪ فجأة، لم أعد أسأل أبداً ♪
♪ About the lingering warmth upon waking ♪
♪ عن الدفء المتبقي عند الاستيقاظ ♪
♪ This unexpected sincerity ♪
♪ هذه الصراحة غير المتوقعة ♪
♪ Makes each of our lives complete ♪
♪ يجعل حياة كل واحد منا كاملة ♪
♪ I can't quite describe it ♪
♪ لا أستطيع وصفه تماماً ♪
♪ A sudden, unexpected surprise ♪
♪ مفاجأة مفاجئة وغير متوقعة ♪
♪ Don't go away too fast ♪
♪ لا ترحل بسرعة كبيرة ♪
♪ It truly exists ♪
♪ إنها موجودة بالفعل ♪
♪ Thank you for your generosity ♪
♪ شكرًا لك على كرمك ♪
♪ For making me believe in love ♪
♪ لأنكِ جعلتني أؤمن بالحب ♪
You put it on?
هل ارتديته؟
Our house hasn't been this lively in a long time.
لم يكن منزلنا بهذه الحيوية منذ فترة طويلة.
Grandma.
جدتي.
Uncle,
عم،
Auntie,
يا خالتي،
I would like to ask for your permission to marry Laili.
أود أن أطلب إذنك للزواج من ليلى.
He's proposing to her.
إنه يتقدم لخطبتها.
I will definitely make Laili happy.
سأجعل ليلى سعيدة بالتأكيد.
I am sincere.
أنا صادق.
Please believe me.
صدقني من فضلك.
No.
لا.
You can't agree so easily.
لا يمكنك الموافقة بهذه السهولة.
Arzugul.
الجشع.
Whose side are you on?
مع من تقف؟
No, no.
لا لا.
I will definitely ask my grandpa and parents
سأسأل جدي ووالديّ بالتأكيد
to come and propose in person.
أن يأتي ويتقدم بطلب الزواج شخصياً.
Right.
يمين.
That's more like it.
هذا أفضل.
Congratulations, young man.
تهانينا أيها الشاب.
Congratulations.
تهانينا.
Laili, congratulations.
ليلي، ألف مبروك.
If only Minawar were here.
ليت ميناوار كان هنا.
Come, have a baked bun.
تفضل، خذ كعكة مخبوزة.
Grandma!
جدتي!
Mom, what's wrong?
أمي، ما بكِ؟
Hurry, take her to the hospital.
أسرعوا، خذوها إلى المستشفى.
Minawar?
ميناوار؟
Grandma.
جدتي.
You're here, my granddaughter.
أنتِ هنا يا حفيدتي.
She cut her hair.
قصت شعرها.
You scared me to death.
لقد أرعبتني حتى الموت.
It's okay.
لا بأس.
It seems I can live a few more days.
يبدو أنني أستطيع أن أعيش لبضعة أيام أخرى.
Don't say that.
لا تقل ذلك.
Auntie, get some good rest. It's fine.
يا خالتي، خذي قسطاً من الراحة. لا بأس.
Children.
أطفال.
I know
أنا أعرف
my own body.
جسدي.
I have something to tell you.
لدي شيء أريد أن أخبرك به.
Minawar.
ميناوار.
I haven't seen the snow mountains for many years.
لم أرَ الجبال الثلجية منذ سنوات عديدة.
My lovely pigeon.
حمامتي الجميلة.
Thank you
شكرًا لك
for coming with me to see the snow mountains.
لأنك أتيت معي لرؤية الجبال الثلجية.
All my life,
طوال حياتي،
I've been my husband's wife,
لقد كنت زوجة زوجي،
my children's mother,
والدة أطفالي،
and your grandmother.
وجدتك.
I feel very happy.
أشعر بسعادة بالغة.
But
لكن
my only regret is
ندمي الوحيد هو
that I've spent my whole life living here
أنني قضيت حياتي كلها أعيش هنا
and never left.
ولم يغادر أبداً.
So in my next life,
لذا في حياتي القادمة،
I want to be a pigeon,
أريد أن أصبح حمامة،
soaring and gliding through the blue sky
التحليق والانزلاق عبر السماء الزرقاء
to see the world.
لرؤية العالم.
That would be great.
سيكون ذلك رائعاً.
You will, Grandma.
ستفعلين ذلك يا جدتي.
♪ We have crossed countless perils ♪
♪ لقد تجاوزنا مخاطر لا حصر لها ♪
♪ We have scaled high mountains ♪
♪ لقد تسلقنا جبالاً شاهقة ♪
♪ Opening our arms to those in the wind and rain ♪
♪ نفتح أذرعنا لمن يواجهون الرياح والأمطار ♪
♪ When liberation comes ♪
♪ عندما يأتي التحرر ♪
♪ Sunlight will shine across the land ♪
♪ ستشرق الشمس على الأرض ♪
♪ The thick mist has already dispersed ♪
♪ لقد تبدد الضباب الكثيف بالفعل ♪
♪ Opening our arms to those in the wind and rain ♪
♪ نفتح أذرعنا لمن يواجهون الرياح والأمطار ♪
♪ When liberation comes ♪
♪ عندما يأتي التحرر ♪
♪ It is our sacred duty ♪
♪ إنه واجبنا المقدس ♪
Laili.
ليلي.
How is it?
كيف هذا؟
Does it feel familiar?
هل يبدو الأمر مألوفاً؟
I didn't expect
لم أتوقع
you to decorate this place like this.
يمكنك تزيين هذا المكان على هذا النحو.
Do you like it?
هل أحببت ذلك؟
I really love it.
أحبه حقاً.
Scoop out a big round piece,
استخرج قطعة دائرية كبيرة،
just like we did when we were kids.
تمامًا كما كنا نفعل عندما كنا أطفالًا.
I thought
ظننت
that after this place was renovated,
بعد تجديد هذا المكان،
our secret base from childhood
قاعدتنا السرية منذ الطفولة
would no longer exist.
لن يكون موجوداً بعد الآن.
How could that be?
كيف يمكن أن يكون ذلك؟
Exactly, how could that be?
بالضبط، كيف يمكن أن يكون ذلك؟
Guess which girl I saw Sadiq with
خمنوا مع أي فتاة رأيت صادق
at the cinema last week?
في السينما الأسبوع الماضي؟
What's there to guess?
ما الذي يمكن تخمينه؟
It was Gulistan.
كانت جولستان.
How do you know?
كيف علمت بذلك؟
He's single now.
هو أعزب الآن.
He can watch movies with whoever he wants.
بإمكانه مشاهدة الأفلام مع من يشاء.
You are so open-minded.
أنت منفتح الذهن للغاية.
Yeah.
نعم.
Actually,
في الحقيقة،
I thought about it for a long time.
لقد فكرت في الأمر لفترة طويلة.
It was not that he didn't love me.
لم يكن الأمر أنه لم يكن يحبني.
It was just
كان الأمر كذلك فقط
that the way he loved me wasn't what I wanted.
أن الطريقة التي أحبني بها لم تكن ما أريده.
Then before...
ثم قبل ذلك...
It was my own choice to marry someone I didn't love.
كان قراري أن أتزوج شخصاً لا أحبه.
But you had the courage to bear everything after,
لكنك تحليت بالشجاعة لتحمل كل شيء بعد ذلك،
right?
يمين؟
Arzugul, what about you and Zhou Hengzhi?
أرزوغول، ماذا عنك أنت وتشو هنغتشي؟
A homestay in Zhejiang
إقامة منزلية في تشجيانغ
saw how I renovated our place
رأيت كيف قمت بتجديد منزلنا
and reached out to me.
وتواصل معي.
That's a good thing.
هذا شيء جيد.
Then...
ثم...
Are you leaving again?
هل ستغادر مجدداً؟
Honestly, my time back here
بصراحة، الوقت الذي قضيته هنا
has been like a robot vacuum
لقد كان أشبه بمكنسة كهربائية آلية
returning to its docking station:
العودة إلى محطة الإرساء الخاصة بها:
emptying the trash
إفراغ سلة المهملات
and getting fully recharged.
وإعادة شحنها بالكامل.
I can set off again.
يمكنني الانطلاق مجدداً.
Does Zhou Hengzhi know?
هل يعلم تشو هنغتشي؟
Whether he supports you or not,
سواء كان يدعمك أم لا،
we definitely support you.
نحن ندعمك بكل تأكيد.
Support you forever.
سأدعمك للأبد.
You're my backup.
أنت سندي.
No one is allowed to run away.
لا يُسمح لأحد بالهرب.
You have to be here,
يجب أن تكون هنا،
and you have to be here, too.
ويجب أن تكون أنت هنا أيضاً.
Hey Minawar, I really want to see you dance.
يا ميناوار، أريد حقاً أن أراك ترقص.
I want to see it, too.
أريد أن أراه أيضاً.
Are you ready?
هل أنت مستعد؟
Okay, let's start.
حسنًا، لنبدأ.
3, 2, 1.
3، 2، 1.
You startled me.
لقد فاجأتني.
That was the point.
كان هذا هو الهدف.
What are you doing here?
ما الذي تفعله هنا؟
Don't you go surprising me
لا تفاجئني
by pulling a ring out of thin air in a moment.
عن طريق سحب خاتم من العدم في لحظة.
Are...
نكون...
Are you really going to?
هل ستفعل ذلك حقاً؟
Xia Zi,
شيا زي,
I don't have a ring for you.
ليس لدي خاتم لكِ.
You scared me to death.
لقد أرعبتني حتى الموت.
But
لكن
I have a gift for you.
لدي هدية لك.
Check it out.
تحقق من ذلك.
I know you want to go.
أعلم أنك تريد الذهاب.
It will be a bigger stage.
سيكون ذلك على مسرح أكبر.
You can
أنت تستطيع
unleash your talent there.
أطلق العنان لموهبتك هناك.
And this place and I
وهذا المكان وأنا
shouldn't hold you back.
لا ينبغي أن يعيقك ذلك.
It's not that urgent.
الأمر ليس بهذه الأهمية.
I'll go after everything is settled here.
سأذهب بعد أن يتم تسوية كل شيء هنا.
Who are you looking down on?
من تحتقر؟
I'm the most professional when it comes to homestays.
أنا الأكثر احترافية عندما يتعلق الأمر بالإقامة مع العائلات.
Besides,
بجانب،
there are Uncle, Auntie,
هناك عم، وعمة،
and everyone else.
والجميع الآخرين.
Aren't you worried?
ألا تشعر بالقلق؟
In that case,
في هذه الحالة،
don't go.
لا تذهب.
Your mom told me
أخبرتني والدتك
the story of her and your Dad.
قصة علاقتها بوالدك.
The land here is so vast.
الأرض هنا شاسعة للغاية.
Love shouldn't be narrow.
لا ينبغي أن يكون الحب محدوداً.
I hope you can become better.
أتمنى أن تتحسن حالتك.
I'll be
سأكون
waiting for you here.
أنتظرك هنا.
Go.
يذهب.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Think of me when you're out there.
تذكرني عندما تكون هناك.
W-When I'm unhappy,
عندما أكون غير سعيد،
I carve one of these for myself.
أقوم بنحت واحدة من هذه لنفسي.
Come back if you're unhappy.
عد إلينا إذا لم تكن راضياً.
You must come back soon.
يجب أن تعود قريباً.
After all, a man's prime
ففي نهاية المطاف، ذروة الرجل
doesn't last that long.
لا يدوم طويلاً.
You are so shameless.
أنت عديم الحياء للغاية.
♪ The sun goes down, but tomorrow it will climb again ♪
♪ تغرب الشمس، لكنها ستشرق من جديد غداً ♪
♪ Flowers fade, but next year they will bloom again ♪
♪ تذبل الأزهار، لكنها ستزهر من جديد في العام المقبل ♪
♪ The beautiful bird is gone without a trace ♪
♪ اختفى الطائر الجميل دون أثر ♪
♪ My youth, like that bird, will never come back again ♪
♪ شبابي، مثل ذلك الطائر، لن يعود أبداً ♪
♪ Here, I have spent ♪
♪ هنا، قضيت ♪
♪ A long vacation ♪
♪ إجازة طويلة ♪
♪ Here, I have found ♪
♪ هنا، وجدتُ ♪
♪ The self within my heart ♪
♪ الذات الكامنة في قلبي ♪
♪ We will always be the best for one another ♪
♪ سنكون دائماً الأفضل لبعضنا البعض ♪
♪ Hand in hand, side by side ♪
♪ يداً بيد، جنباً إلى جنب ♪
♪ Witnessing each other's first times ♪
♪ يشهدان تجارب بعضهما الأولى ♪
♪ There are some things ♪
♪ هناك بعض الأشياء ♪
♪ That I entrust only to you in this life ♪
♪ أنني لا أوكل أمر هذا إلا إليك في هذه الحياة ♪
♪ You are the one who talked with me until dawn ♪
♪ أنتِ من تحدثتِ معي حتى الفجر ♪
♪ Let all the secrets be buried in the wind and sand ♪
♪ دع كل الأسرار تُدفن في الريح والرمال ♪
♪ Those moments of madness and hardship ♪
♪ تلك اللحظات من الجنون والمشقة ♪
♪ Were scattered by the wind and turned into courage ♪
♪ تشتتت بفعل الريح وتحولت إلى شجاعة ♪
♪ That eternal, quiet peace ♪
♪ ذلك السلام الأبدي الهادئ ♪
♪ Gives me courage ♪
♪ يمنحني الشجاعة ♪
♪ Consistent as ever ♪
♪ ثابتون كالعادة ♪
♪ Deeply rooted in my heart ♪
♪ متجذرة بعمق في قلبي ♪
♪ On the streets of Kashgar ♪
♪ في شوارع كاشغر ♪
♪ Holding hands ♪
♪ يمسكان بأيدي بعضهما البعض ♪
♪ Setting off just like that, walking toward forever ♪
♪ انطلقنا هكذا، نسير نحو الأبدية ♪
♪ The uncertain, the swaying ♪
♪ غير المؤكد، المتأرجح ♪
♪ There is still time ♪
♪ لا يزال هناك وقت ♪
♪ Steadying oneself, within reach ♪
♪ تثبيت النفس، في متناول اليد ♪
♪ At the entrance of the post house ♪
♪ عند مدخل مكتب البريد ♪
♪ Holding hands once more ♪
♪ يمسكان بأيدي بعضهما مرة أخرى ♪
♪ Dear friend, the pomegranates are fully ripe ♪
♪ صديقي العزيز، لقد نضج الرمان تماماً ♪
♪ Being a wife, being a mother ♪
♪ أن تكوني زوجة، أن تكوني أماً ♪
♪ A woman surrounded by love ♪
♪ امرأة محاطة بالحب ♪
♪ I use love to illuminate ♪
♪ أستخدم الحب للإضاءة ♪
♪ Warming my daughters ♪
♪ تدفئة بناتي ♪
♪ Daughters ♪
♪ بنات ♪
♪ We are the family who loves you forever ♪
♪ نحن العائلة التي تحبك إلى الأبد ♪
♪ Home will always keep its doors open for you ♪
♪ سيظل المنزل يفتح أبوابه لك دائمًا ♪
But Dad,
لكن يا أبي،
a girl's hands can mold clay,
بإمكان يدي الفتاة تشكيل الطين،
and they can also dance.
ويمكنهم أيضاً الرقص.
♪ Writing love and hope into songs ♪
♪ كتابة الحب والأمل في الأغاني ♪
♪ Letting the whole world sing along with me ♪
♪ دع العالم كله يغني معي ♪
♪ Holding my love for you in the palms of my hands ♪
♪ أحمل حبي لك بين راحتيّ ♪
♪ I cherish it carefully with you ♪
♪ أعتز بها معك بعناية ♪
♪ I treat you with sincere devotion, always ♪
♪ أعاملك بإخلاصٍ تام، دائماً ♪
♪ Without fearing the eyes of others ♪
♪ دون خوف من نظرات الآخرين ♪
♪ Looking back at you after enduring the wind and rain ♪
♪ أنظر إليكِ بعد أن تحملتِ الرياح والأمطار ♪
♪ Love and courage make us shine ♪
♪ الحب والشجاعة يجعلاننا نتألق ♪
♪ La la la, I am here ♪
♪ لا لا لا، أنا هنا ♪
♪ Spending my youth, I found you ♪
♪ قضيتُ شبابي، فوجدتكِ ♪
♪ La, la, la, I am here ♪
♪ لا، لا، لا، أنا هنا ♪
♪ Writing an eternal melody ♪
♪ كتابة لحن أبدي ♪
On the way to set off again,
في طريقنا للانطلاق مجدداً،
I had a dream.
حلمت حلماً.
In the dream, I heard the sound of the Satar again.
في الحلم، سمعت صوت الساتار مرة أخرى.
♪ The lover I long for ♪
♪ الحبيب الذي أتوق إليه ♪
♪ May you live for a thousand years ♪
♪ أتمنى لك عمراً مديداً ♪
♪ May your tears hold no sorrow ♪
♪ عسى ألا تحمل دموعك حزناً ♪
♪ Since I saw you, my lover ♪
♪ منذ أن رأيتك يا حبيبي ♪
♪ I have fallen into a pit of distress ♪
♪ لقد سقطت في حفرة من الضيق ♪
♪ You set a fire in my heart ♪
♪ أشعلتَ نارًا في قلبي ♪
In the dream,
في الحلم،
just as a poet said,
كما قال الشاعر،
the people and things that exist in memory,
الأشخاص والأشياء التي تبقى في الذاكرة،
the past and the future,
الماضي والمستقبل،
the sound of music and dance,
صوت الموسيقى والرقص،
the streets and houses,
الشوارع والمنازل،
day and night,
ليلاً ونهاراً،
and reality and illusion—
والحقيقة والوهم—
they all intermingle,
يختلطون جميعاً،
blended like milk tea.
ممزوج مثل شاي الحليب.
The milk and tea become inseparable,
يصبح الحليب والشاي لا ينفصلان،
leaving a lingering fragrance that fills the senses.
يترك عبيراً فواحاً يملأ الحواس.
I once grew weary
لقد شعرت بالتعب ذات مرة
and returned to my hometown
وعدت إلى مسقط رأسي
for a nap.
لأخذ قيلولة.
I had a vivid, colorful dream
حلمت حلماً واضحاً وملوناً
where I laughed out loud,
حيث ضحكت بصوت عالٍ،
cried my heart out,
بكيتُ بحرقة،
sang at the top of my lungs,
غنيت بأعلى صوتي،
and danced with abandon.
ورقصوا بحماسٍ شديد.
When I woke up,
عندما استيقظت،
I set off again,
انطلقت مجدداً،
no longer afraid.
لم أعد خائفاً.
[Dedicated to us, as we set out once more]
[مُهدى إلينا، ونحن ننطلق من جديد]